Welcome everybody. We are a week into
free agency and half most of the moves,
primary moves, are done. So, it's a good
point for us to sit here and kind of
evaluate what the Patriots have done. I
think it's a pretty interesting way
they've approached this because they
didn't really sign any of their own
guys, right? Like they kind of let
everybody walk. Interesting to me, but
also a sign that I think they realized
they're still building. They get some
new players in and I want to start on
the offensive side of the ball where it
felt like an injection of Josh
McDaniels, an injection of some
toughness, something I think this team
needed with the addition I mean, let's
just run them down. I mean, Reggie
Gilliam, let's start with him. They got
a fullback now, a real fullback.
>> a real fullback. You know, Jaleel Hill,
obviously blocking tight end, a guard.
Uh you got your people got Romeo Doubs,
all right. So, we got one wide receiver
in there, but I think that you you
nailed it.
Last year, they're 25th in the league in
rush EPA. They're down near the bottom
of the league in terms of short yardage
runs and goal line runs and a success
rate in those situations. And that just
doesn't feel like a Mike Vrabel team.
Like a team that can't just uh put some
big boys up there on the line of
scrimmage when they need a yard and pick
up a yard on the ground. They had to
find ways to have a little bit more of
that kind of identity. Not just rushing
the ball efficiently, but just from an
identity standpoint of being a physical
team, being a team that can win in the
trenches and win in those margins. So,
uh overall, we we talk a lot about this
kind of stuff in December and January
when it matters and they're got fourth
and one for the season. It's not sexy in
March, but it's big in January,
hopefully February when the games come
down to those you you really literally
inches sometimes on those short yardage
situations. Yeah, Reggie Gilliam, number
44. I mean, we got this is a real This
is a legit fullback, finally. And you
take him from Buffalo, you kind of
weaken them a little bit. Love that. I I
just want to point out Elijah
Vera-Tucker though, which you know, it's
a move that I love in free agency where
you have a talented guy. He's missed a
couple years, you know, with injuries.
He's torn both triceps. Uh it's been a
little bit of a struggle for him to stay
healthy, but if he does stay healthy,
we've been talking about the offensive
line. We know, you know, that was
something down the stretch in the
playoffs that they really needed a boost
in. It seems like pencil in him in to
that left guard spot. You let Garrett
Bradbury, you know, trade him. Slide
Jared Wilson over. You were on top of
this earlier. You started this
offseason, you were like, let's go get a
left guard. I like this move. I like
this move.
>> you know, I think the the thing that I
like the most about it is that it was
kind of common sense move just looking
at their options about the offensive
line. And uh when we talked to Elliot
Wolf last week, he just said, "Hey,
look, if there's a better left tackle
than Will Campbell with the 31st pick in
the draft, then by all means, like we
would be open to something like that,
but that's not reality. And we know how
this works at that position. It's very
seldom that starting caliber, franchise
caliber left tackles are available in
the veteran market. If you draft them,
they got to you got to draft them high.
It's not going to, you know, fall to you
at 31 or on day two of the draft. So,
it's one of those positions that's at a
premium right now. Uh so, the best case
scenario was, let's give Will Campbell
at least another year. Let's see if the
pre-injury Will Campbell is the guy that
they get moving forward instead of what
we saw in the postseason with the, you
know, knee limitations.
Jared Wilson goes back to his natural
position at center, which hopefully
upgrades both him and the center
position long term. And you get a guy
like Elijah Vera-Tucker who is a very uh
high-level pass protector, a veteran guy
that's got experience, a guy that has
knowledge of the game to put between the
two young centers. And hopefully that
just all tides rise, you know, all at
once with that. So, you get a little bit
better, healthier version of Will
Campbell. You get a little bit better
Jared Wilson at his natural spot at
center. And then you get a better, you
know, more kind of experienced, more
sturdy option there at left guard. I
know there's been a lot of talk about
A.J. Brown and trade rumors and all that
kind of stuff. Seems like now maybe
we're waiting till June for something
like that to to get any traction. But
let's talk about Romeo Doubs who uh
>> to be closer to 50/50 inside/outside and
now that he's with the Patriots. And
then I just say, you know, he does a lot
of the same things that Stefon Diggs
did. You know, a lot of those possession
receiver routes, third and eight, you
need nine yards, he can get you nine
yards. Is he that big play, explosive,
change the dynamic of the defense, you
know, coverage-dictating receiver?
Probably not. Uh but he's got that
ability to, you know, move the chains.
41 first downs last year for Green Bay.
Diggs had 51 with the Patriots, but on
higher volume. So, if you give him those
20 extra targets this season, you know,
does he close that gap with Stefon
Diggs? I think they're going to be used
very similarly. Let's flip it over to
defense now, where it seems again, like
a little bit of a one-for-one. I mean,
you've got Jaylen Hawkins leaves, signs
with Baltimore, you get Kevin Byard in.
Uh very excited about him. Uh K'Lavon
Chaisson goes on a one-year deal, 12
million, kind of surprising to me.
Thought he would land a multi-year deal.
Patriots go with Dre'Mont Jones. And
similar stats between the two guys, but
you know, a three-year deal there.
Patriots investing in in Jones a little
bit. Jack Gibbons is gone, you bring in
K.J. Britt. Uh you know, so interesting
how they've approached this. I want to
just start with Kevin Byard because I
just love getting talented guys. He's
coming off a huge season last year for
the Bears. Uh another All-Pro, his third
All-Pro season.
S- feels like a little bit of an upgrade
on Jaylen Hawkins. I know he's a little
bit older, but the leadership he brings,
the swagger, and and clearly just the
smarts, his ability to know where the
ball is going to bait quarterbacks into
those kind of throws. Really excited to
see what he brings to this defense.
Yeah, I I think that's what stands out
the most is like this guy reads
quarterbacks like books. You know, it's
unbelievable. I think the combination of
experience in the league that he has now
with the still uh pretty good
athleticism and and speed in in the open
field. Like you combine those two
things, where now he kind of has the
answers to the test, but he also has
probably 90% of the athleticism that he
had in his peak years in Tennessee. So,
that makes him still a a very good
player, an All-Pro safety. Last year,
led the league in interceptions. So, you
put all these things together of like
the smarts, the ball-hawking instincts,
the intelligence out there, where like
he's literally just reading route
combinations. Like he knows, okay, this
guy's clearing me out. They're trying to
open the space to this guy. I'm just
going to sit here and jump this route.
Uh so, I I think that those are really
encouraging things. And uh you know,
let's face it, they they weren't a
defense that turned the ball over very
much last year. As good as they were,
especially down the stretch in the
playoffs, turnovers was one thing that
they really talked about all year
wanting to create more turnovers. Well,
you just went out and got the guy that
led the league in interceptions a year
ago. So, if you want to create more
turnovers, get guys that turn the ball
over.
>> [laughter]
>> And that's what they got with Kevin
Byard. So, it's you know, like I said,
it's a lot of one-for-one. It doesn't
really necessarily feel like there's a
super upgrade. I mean, maybe Byard you
could say, but you know, I still as we
look at this is their initial part of
free agency. There's still other parts
to go. There's still trades that could
happen. I know, you know, Jonathan
Greenard from Minnesota who we saw last
summer, who I think is, you know, an
outstanding player. I still look at guys
like him because I think they need more
on the edge still. And that's a position
that, you know, as much as Dre'Mont
Jones maybe has some untapped potential,
at the same time, you don't know what to
expect from Harold Landry coming off,
you know, a season where he was
experiencing injuries. He's getting up
there. Elijah Ponder still a little bit
of an unknown. Anthony Jennings gets
released. So, as we sit here at this
point, a week into free agency, I still
look at that position. And as I
mentioned earlier, the wide receiver
one. We're always looking for that kind
of guy who can change the game. You
know, what's your impression right now
of what they need going forward?
>> Yeah, I I mean, edge rusher to me and I
kind of look at it like if the season
were to start tomorrow, how would you
feel about each position group? And I
look at wide receiver and I still still
feel that urge to have that superstar,
that number one, you know, prototypical
number one receiver like they had last
year with Diggs. But I look at edge as
one that could really be a house of
cards because we don't really know what
you're getting out of Harold Landry
coming off that knee injury. I like
Dre'Mont Jones. I think he's a little
bit more physical, maybe a little bit
more sturdier than K'Lavon Chaisson, but
that's a wash. I mean, that's a
one-for-one exchange there. So,
not knowing what you're going to get
from Landry both availability-wise and
production-wise. Like you're putting a
lot of eggs in the Elijah Ponder, Braden
Swinson basket to have a fifth-round
pick and a UDFA make the leap, so to
speak. So, I look at edge as a
sure-fire, you know, top two picks, you
know, whether it's at 31 or 63. Like it
just feels like a guarantee that one of
those picks is going to be an edge
rusher.
So, you know, it's a good class and and
they could probably get away with
drafting one of those players there and
getting something out of them, but
particularly that ability to rush the
passer, purely rush the passer with
speed off the edge because we don't know
what kind of guy Landry is going to be
at this stage of his career. Uh wide
receiver, we're always going to talk
about the need for uh you know, that
number one guy until they get it solved
in the long term, so that remains, but
the other positions that I look at just
from needs is more long-term needs of
having guys in the pipeline to take over
for older guys. Looking at right tackle
with Morgan Moses, tight end with Hunter
Henry, linebacker with Robert Spillane,
safety now with Kevin Byard. You know,
these are the positions you know, maybe
you can get into cornerback too with
that with Carlton Davis. Like you got to
start preparing for the next chapter at
all these spots, but it sounds like a
lot, but I would say the positive is
that it's not starters. Like you're not
asking a third-round pick at right
tackle to be drafted and start like they
were a couple years ago with Kaden
Wallace. Now you're just asking him to
be the swing tackle as a rookie and then
hopefully down the line replace Morgan
Moses. So they don't have to throw any
of these rookies into the fire, but they
do need to start preparing for life
after some of those veteran players.
Yeah, so it's like you're teasing
Patriots Draft Countdown a little bit.
We get into and check out this week's
episode where we talk about how did free
agency really affect the draft plans of
the team? And you mentioned edge, I mean
all those positions, tight end. These
are positions linebacker that we've
heard Mike Vrabel, Eliot Wolf say are
positions of strength in the draft. So
when I you know, we give you a little
tease right here, but when I look at the
moves they make, it seems to set up
nicely for let's get into the draft.
We're going to find maybe a right tackle
of the future, maybe that edge to start
working in and get starter reps. And
that's what good teams do, dude. Like I
like good teams are a draft and develop
organizations that stay ahead of these
things. When the Patriots are really
humming during the dynasty years with
Belichick and Brady, that's what they
were doing. It was Matt Light to Nate
Solder. It was like having succession
plans all over the roster uh so that you
weren't caught in situations where you
know, you have guys like towards the end
where Gronk, you know, moves on and then
you don't have any tight ends. Like
that's what you don't want to run into.
So I think that they have really set
themselves up and I know some people you
mentioned off the top of the show are
surprised that they moved on from a lot
of their internal free agents. Well,
when you think about it, I think a lot
of that was to set up opportunities for
some of these younger guys. Like if you
just bring all those guys back, then
where's the roster spots, where's the
roles for these young draft picks to
come in and step in and play a little
bit as rookies. So we're looking at you
know, Vederian Lowe goes, well there now
you got your swing tackle spot. Jack
Gibbons and Jelani Tavai goes, well now
you have you know, ability to have depth
at linebacker from a rookie. Safety, you
know, you move on from Jalen Hawkins.
You know, all these different spots.
Austin Hooper, you know, leaves and goes
to Atlanta at tight end. So now you have
opportunities for these younger players
to actually
contribute and roles on the team. Heck,
have [music] roster spots, period, that
hopefully they can develop into
starters. It's amazing how much changes
in just a week of free agency. You know,
you know, a week ago we're looking here,
we don't know what's going to happen.
Now they've got some new guys, they've
set the table here for this 2026
off-season, but just because the first
week of free agency is over, doesn't
mean that they're done making moves. So
stay tuned, of course, and check out the
Patriots Draft Countdown podcast where
we'll get into the draft, what the needs
are, what the strengths of this draft
are. We got you covered this whole
spring.